hello this is Frank de Freitas and
welcome to hola talk your laser and
holography internet radio talk show I've
been off the air since a week before
Christmas and not only is it good to be
back behind the mic again there's been a
lot of very exciting work that has taken
place in the last few weeks that I'd
like to get everyone back up to speed on
Hollow talk was down completely for
Christmas week due to my Santa radar
page where kids could track Santa from
the North Pole with radar and listen to
updates along the trip the page received
14 055 hits on Christmas Eve and we
received 156 phone calls in three hours
to Santa sleigh during the trip it was a
lot of fun and I'm hoping it turns into
an annual tradition on the web for kids
everywhere
the scheduled guest for this week Arlene
jurowitz has asked to move her
appearance to next week due to a
scheduling conflict so we're looking
forward to hearing about Arlene and her
work with holography hopefully next week
on the show
I'd like to say hello to all new
listeners and I imagine you're going to
have a lot of you out there especially
those interested in laser pointer
holography which has become a very hot
topic as your emails have shown over the
past several weeks
since the last show right before
Christmas and by the way whole talk is
now back on the air with a new show
every week until Memorial Day after
Memorial Day you can enjoy the summer
rebroadcast until the new fall season
anyway since the last show before
Christmas we have moved from wondering
if laser pointers will consistently work
for making Holograms to actually
creating a multiple color reflection
hologram using one
there are two areas of laser pointer
holography that I am very interested in
I will tell you what those areas are and
why I feel they are important to the
success of this new sub field of
traditional quote-unquote holography
my first area of Interest with
development is multi-colored laser
pointer holography this is where you can
have the Hologram exhibit color control
and mixing of several colors at one time
I find this very important in order to
make holography appealing to artists who
wish to give it a shot as a means of
creative expression I have managed to
create a four by five inch multi-color
white light reflection hologram single
beam hologram using my later laser
pointer that I paid 7.99 for
I now have a special section of the
hello world site dedicated to laser
pointer holography so I hope that you
take the opportunity to visit the pages
to see what work has been done in the
last few weeks and continue to visit to
keep up with advancements as they are
made
my second area of interest in making
simple holographic stereograms this is
where you can take a series of
individual pictures from different
perspectives with your own 35 millimeter
camera and then transfer those frames
into one hologram which will give you a
three-dimensional view of your subject
whether it's a nature scene a car or a
portrait of someone that you know maybe
a wife girlfriend boyfriend husband your
child grandchildren you can take them
sit them down do a specific series of
exposures with your 35 millimeter camera
and then get that film processed and
bring it in and create a
three-dimensional hologram from those
frames I find this area important
because of the vast number of amateur
and hobbyist photographers out there
who are always looking to advance their
interests and skills and to try out new
techniques in the past purchasing a
helium neon laser for several hundred
dollars was out of the question but to
be able to do this with a laser pointer
that is less than ten dollar now moves
that restriction out of the way
stereogram Holograms are going to
require a split beam setup
so this is still an area that needs to
be explored at the very least I would
like to be able to create the laser
transmission stereogram slit Master this
would give you an opportunity to view
the Hologram with the laser pointer and
see it three-dimensionally doing the
transfer from the laser Master to a
reflection copy is going to be a long
shot at the low power end of laser
pointers
but this is what the work is all about
you push the limits you have to think
differently and you have to come up with
answers and solutions
the one advantage of creating
stereograms is that the dimensional
information is contained within a flat
plane for example the three-dimensional
image that you see when you look at a
sterigram is not due to the fact that
there is a three-dimensional object
recorded onto the Emulsion as in typical
traditional holography where you see an
object behind the plate you do a
holographic Master of the object and
then transfer that over that's an actual
wave front of the object that's
traveling out there the fact that you
see a three-dimens dimensional image
when you look at a stereogram is due to
the fact that your eyes are seeing
different perspectives at the same time
and this information is contained as a
flat plane which requires very little
coherence length providing that your
table geometry is set up properly and
your B pads match up as closely to one
another as you can possibly make them
I have also found that Hitachi has just
released
35 milliwatt 658 nanometer laser diode
for 41 dollars
this is 35 milliwatts for 41 dollars
call your laser supplier and ask them to
quote you a price on a 35 milliwatt
helium neon laser you're looking at
several thousand dollars
Steve Michael will be back with updates
on his experimentation and research as
well on future Hall talks at present he
is working with kodak's so253 film to
see how well it works out I'm going to
order some of the slavage filament
plates in the not too distant future and
begin working with them as well I just
opened my last box of ad for plates and
still have a few packs of film left but
after that that's it for iPhone I have
nothing else
Steve is also working with split beam
holography according to his last email
that he just sent today to see if it's
possible to get results and what those
results are
now I highly recommend that you visit
and bookmark Steve's site for additional
information and updates you can find a
link to Steve's site on my link page and
I've created a special section right at
the cop devoted to laser pointer
holography so stop back and watch it
grow if you have started to work with
laser pointers and have a web page
please send along your url so I can put
a link up for visitors to stop by your
site and see what it is that you're
doing
so get the prices of laser values going
down along with their power increases
and shorter wavelengths this is a very
interesting time indeed my helium neon
laser is just sitting there on the table
I pick up one of those 35 milliwatt
Hitachi diodes and if it works I doubt
that I will use it again
it's true that making Holograms with a
laser pointer or diode or semiconductor
or solid state or whatever term you wish
to use for it is going to take a little
adjustment in the usual way of making
Holograms power requirements beam
profile mode hopping noise changes in
wavelength and power due to temperature
and current and voltage fluctuations and
a host of other considerations not yet
known will have to be worked out and
that's what we're doing
so if you're an artist she's basically
interested in with the creative end of
using this a lot of this information you
may not have very much interest in but
at this stage of the ball game this
inflammation is very important because
this is actually being developed as we
go along here if you continue to stop
back to the laser page that I have up
there for laser diodes and also Steve's
wonderful site
you'll start to see a lot of this
technical information start to fade away
because it's been worked out and it's no
longer necessary to post the findings
and as time goes on
will try and at least on my site I'm
sure Steve as well to cater to the
interest of the amateur and artists and
people who want to use this who are more
interested in actually just taking this
technology and using it rather than
knowing um
how much of a wavelength shift you get
from going from 2.5 volts to 3 volts at
such and such milliamps but we need to
do that right now it's something we need
to do
so hang in there with us
so in other words if you're listening to
this program as a first time listener or
a well-seasoned amateur hobbyist
logically there's plenty of work left to
be done and miles of Road left to travel
at least we know where we're at right
now at this moment and that is we can
make a four by five inch multi-color
single beam reflection hologram
which are every bit as good as what you
would make with an equivalent helium
neon laser the only difference I found
so far
is that it costs less than ten dollars
for the laser pointer
for the experimenter or classroom
teacher
I know we are just about ready to cross
over into what I am calling shoebox
holography where your entire political
system fits into the area the size of a
shoe box
with no electricity required in fact I
have classes starting this spring at the
Discovery Center at Lehigh University
which I am calling shoebox holography
and if you would like to learn how to do
laser pointer holography through a
workshop in my studio I'll have
information on that up on the web soon
as well
you'll even be able to take home
everything you need to start making your
own Holograms from the workshop
including the laser the lens the plate
holder film development chemistry and
little isolation platform and I'll even
put it into a shoe box for you of course
I have size 12 shoes so that helps when
it comes to fitting everything into the
box
so that's it for this week's report
let's keep it short have you go over and
visit the laser pointer pages and see
what's happening with the laser pointers
and also don't forget to go over and
visit Steve's site and also don't forget
to tune in each week for hollow talk as
we've got lots of guests coming up on
the second half of the season
if you have any news please send it in
so that I can share it with everyone so
this is Frankie Freitas thanks for
tuning in and see you next week
thanks